<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miranda, stupenda. Or, The wonderfull and astonishing mercies which the Lord hath wrought for England, in subduing and captivating the pride, power and policy of his enemies. Presented in a sermon preached July 21. 1646. before the honorable House of Commons in Margarets Church Westm. being the day appointed for thanksgiving for the surrender of Oxford. / By Henry Wilkinson, B.D. pastor of Dunstans in the East, London, and one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1610-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E345_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861585</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E345[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miranda, stupenda. Or, The wonderfull and astonishing mercies which the Lord hath wrought for England, in subduing and captivating the pride, power and policy of his enemies. Presented in a sermon preached July 21. 1646. before the honorable House of Commons in Margarets Church Westm. being the day appointed for thanksgiving for the surrender of Oxford. / By Henry Wilkinson, B.D. pastor of Dunstans in the East, London, and one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1610-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Christopher Meredith and Samuel Gellibrand in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Order to print on recto of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XXIII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113723:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Miranda, Stupenda. OR, THE WONDERFVLL and aſtoniſhing Mercies which the LORD hath wrought for ENGLAND, in ſubduing and captivating the pride, power and policy of his enemies. PRESENTED IN A SERMON PREACHED <hi>July</hi> 21. 1646. Before the honorable Houſe of COMMONS in <hi>Margarets</hi> Church <hi>Weſtm.</hi> being the day appointed for Thankſgiving for the Surrender of <hi>OXFORD.</hi> By HENRY WILKINSON, <hi>B. D.</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Dunstans</hi> in the Eaſt, <hi>London,</hi> and one of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>EXOD. 15. 11.</bibl> 
               <hi>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, among the gods! who is like unto thee, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in holineſſe, fearfull in praiſes, doing wonders!</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Christopher Meredith</hi> and <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113723:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE HOVSE OF <hi>COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS</hi> Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is impoſſible to travell in a great Road, or take his journey to a great Emporium, but he muſt needs meet with paſſengers in his way; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if I have fallen in with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of others, I ſuppoſe I ſhall be no more blamed then they, who writing of poverty or griefe, or death, have made uſe of</hi> Seneca <hi>or</hi> Plutarch. <hi>or they that have handled Politiques, have conſulted with</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>maximes, or have borrowed of</hi> Thucidides, <hi>and</hi> Tacitus, <hi>and</hi> Polybius, <hi>and</hi> Philip de Comines, <hi>and</hi> Lipſius &amp; Guicciardine <hi>who have ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red excellent notions concerning that ſubject; only herein I muſt crave pardon, that treating on the ſame argument which others have handled, there is wanting that skill and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113723:3"/> 
               <hi>excellency in the handling of it: It was the unhappineſſe of</hi> Silius Italicus <hi>to come after</hi> Virgil, <hi>and handle the ſame thing; and ſo alſo of</hi> Grotius <hi>to treat of the ſame matter with</hi> Tacitus, <hi>and of</hi> Paulus Jovius <hi>to be engaged in the ſubject with</hi> Titus Livius: <hi>Yet certainly it is ſo with the choyceſt works of the beſt Divines, we may ſubſcribe them as I find at the end of divers famous Authors,</hi> plurima deſunt &amp; multa deſiderantur; <hi>and many have been as happy in their ſupplements and additionals, and</hi> conjecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea, <hi>as the Authors the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves in the main ſubject. You were pleaſed to call me to preach upon the occaſion of the rendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Oxford, <hi>and alſo you have comanded me to print the Sermon: had I all the learning of a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, I could as willingly have laid it out in the behalfe of that place, and upon this ſubject which I have ſpent my thoughts upon as any other whatſoever. I have made bold to propound ſome things to your conſideration concerning</hi> Oxford, <hi>in order to the reformation of it; which though perhaps they may ſeem to be but contemptible and poore, and ſuch as are never like to riſe to any glorious perfection; yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that he that will build very high, muſt dig low for his foundation; and let not any one despiſe the day of ſmall things, for we know there is no River navigable in the Fountaine, nor any Country where the Sunne ſhines hot at the peeping of the day: Perhaps ſome things may ſeeme ſtrange, but let not any one condemne me for this, becauſe it is a caſe which never was before you till now, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not condemne that for ill which is only extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary; this were to doe as that Norwegian, who when he ſaw red Roſes firſt, he durſt not handle them for feare of burning his fingers. There be ſome will tell you, there is no ſuch need of a reformation of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb facs="tcp:113723:3"/> praiſes for it; but I look upon ſuch as they that are very partiall, as he was that made the Preface to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Statutes, who ſpeaking of Queen</hi> Maries <hi>dayes, hath his</hi> opranda temporum faelicitas <hi>for them; or elſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Eſſays of certaine Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>perhaps they have a mind to exerciſe their wits, as he did which invented prayſes for</hi> Buſyris, <hi>and made an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getique for</hi> Nero, <hi>and Encomiums or</hi> Richard <hi>the third</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh. Donne</hi> his <hi>Juvenilia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Julian <hi>the Apostate; or elſe perhaps they have a mind to imitate ſome whoſe crimes are vertues with them, and paradoxes truths, who maintaine the moſt abſurd things, and inconſistent with truth and piety, onely as a specimen of their wit, to ſhew how they can put a kind of lustre and beauty on a monster. However ſome may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince.</note> 
               <hi>think meanly of this deſigne of yours for the reformation of</hi> Oxford; <hi>yet I think I may truly ſay of this what</hi> Balzac <hi>did of a great enterprize of the French King, that the modesty of an oratory ſtile doth not beſeem an action ſo ſtrange: Poets only have right to that, it appertains to their heroique language; it is worthy of the enthuſiaſme of their pompous and figurative deſcriptions; ſure I am, there is ſcarce any thing more worthy all the contributions which a Parliament can afford, then the ſetling of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity upon the baſis of learning and Religion. You have an opportunity of laying a foundation, and of building too, which ſhall be beyond the reach of envy, againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile; but it ſhall be matter of wonder and rejoycing to ſucceeding generations, who ſhall with triumphant acclamations cry grace, grace, unto it: The Lord that hath called you to work for him, afford you the aſſiſtance of his moſt glorious power, the direction of his infinite wiſedome, and crowne you with incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
<pb facs="tcp:113723:4"/> ſucceſſe here, and give you an immarceſſible crowne of glory hereafter. So prayeth he who counts it his happineſſe to be</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113723:4"/>
            <head>A THANKSGIVING SERMON, Preached before the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of COMMONS, <hi>July</hi> 21. 1646. for the ſurrender of OXFORD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NUMB. 23. 23.</bibl>
                  <p>Surely there is no enhantment againſt Jacob, neither is there any divination againſt Iſrael: According to this time it ſhall be ſaid of Jacob, and of Iſrael, what hath God wrought?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE Words are part of the confeſſion extorted out of the mouth of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who was a Chaplain fit for <hi>Balak</hi> in that curſed deſign of his againſt the Iſraelites, who was reſolved if he could not <hi>flectere ſuperos, Acheronta movere:</hi> Now when this Witch had tryed all his skill in the black Art, and improved all his intereſt in the Devill, he is forced to break out into this acknowledgment, <hi>Surely,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the words there is a Confeſſion firſt; ſecondly, a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113723:5"/> In the Confeſſion, there is his owne ſin implyed; for it is as if he ſhould have ſaid, If divinations, or enchantments, or ſpels, or witchcraft and conjuring in any kind, could have brought downe curſes on Iſrael, they ſhould have been curſed with a vengeance: 2. In the confeſſion there is a tacite acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the over-ruling hand of God, which was too hard for all the powers of darkneſſe, who preſerved Iſrael, maugre all that the wit and ſtrength of malice can doe to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the Declaration there is ſet downe what God had done for his people, or what God might doe, or may doe, or would doe; for the words have all theſe verſions, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; our tranſlation, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Originall: the Sept. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Syriack. <hi>Quid operetur Deus.</hi> The Cald. paraphr. <hi>Quid operatus ſit Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Samaritan pentat. is the ſame with our tranſlat. <hi>Quid fecit Deus;</hi> and this ſhall I follow.</p>
            <p>In all which ſenſes and verſions, we may obſerve; firſt, the ſtrangeneſſe and wonder of the things which God would work for his people: for as it was a very ſtrange thing in the eyes of <hi>Balaam,</hi> that by all his ſorceries he was able to doe no miſchiefe at that time; ſo according to that time for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Lord would preſerve as miraculouſly his ſervants: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, you have the effect that theſe wonders ſhould work in the hearts of them that ſee them, and that is admiration, a ſuitableneſſe of affection to the greatneſſe and wonder of the things wrought by God for his people.</p>
            <p>There be ſeverall Doctrines might be raiſed hence, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the two generals, I will preſent two propoſitions onely: The firſt is a Doctrine of it ſelfe, but you may take it thus:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all the ſorceries, witchcraft and ſtratagems, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and carried on by the wit and malice, and power of hell againſt the Church of God, ſhall prove vaine and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the wonderfull things which God hath wrought and will work for his Church and people, ſhall be, and alſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113723:5"/> are matter of aſtoniſhment and wonder unto all.</p>
            <p>I ſhall inſiſt at preſent on the latter of theſe two Doctrines, as being very ſuitable to our condition in this Kingdome, which of late hath been a theater of wonders, ſo that we may call its name as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 14. of that place where he was to offer <hi>Iſaac, Jehovah jireh.</hi> In the handling of which I ſhal propound, firſt, what things God hath or will work; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, How? thirdly, When? fourthly, Why? fiftly, The Uſes which may be made of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What are the wonders that God hath wrought? Firſt, they be rare, they be ſuch as uſually and frequently are <note place="margin">1. What are the wonders which God hath wrought?</note> not brought to paſſe; ſuch things as happen rarely, are mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of wonder, and draw the eyes of men to them, though they have naturall cauſes; as Eclipſes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Incognita,</hi> ſuch things of which the world is not acquainted withall, whoſe cauſes and ends men cannot reach unto, they being <hi>ultra captum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Inſperata,</hi> ſuch things as are beyond ordinary hopes, ſo they are <hi>ultra ſpem,</hi> as well as <hi>ultra captum,</hi> as being out of the compaſſe of nature, ſuch things are beyond power and parts lying out of the ſpheare of naturall poſſibility.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Repugnantia,</hi> ſuch things as are contrary to the courſe of nature, and are abhorring from the naturall ſtreame and tide of the creature: All things that carry theſe chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters on them are matter of wonder.</p>
            <p>Now the things which God doth for his people, they are <note place="margin">The wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things which God doth for his people are of two ſorts.</note> iether ſpirituall or temporall.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpirituall things in order to ſalvation are indeed <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miranda;</hi> let but any one conſider from whence to what a ſtate we are recovered, and he muſt ſay, as it is, Rom. 11. 33. <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God! &amp;c.</hi> that we ſhould be raiſed from a ſtate of privation, being deveſted of all good; from a ſtate of enmity, againſt all good; a ſtate in which we were lyable to the curſes written and unwritten, &amp;c. to be raiſed from ſo low, and vile, and miſerable, and abominable ſtate, to be the children of God. <hi>John</hi> puts an <hi>Ecce,</hi> a note of admiration on it, 1 <hi>John 3. 1, 2. Behold what manner of love the Father hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113723:6"/> 
               <hi>the ſonnes of God, &amp;c.</hi> That we that ſate in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, ſhould be raiſed up to ſit together in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 6. this is wonderfull, and we may truly ſay, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> That we that have ſo many wayes provoked the Lord to deſtroy us, ſhould be pardoned is wonderfull: the Church ſpeaks of it by way of wonder, Micah 7. 18. <hi>Who is God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage?</hi> Is it not matter of wonder that God ſhould ſay, I, even I am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſion, &amp;c. Iſa. 43. 25. to them he ſpeaks that had not called on him, that were weary of him, that did not ſacrifice to him, that would not ſerve him, but made him to ſerve with their ſinnes, verſe 22, 23. To goe over all the particulars that might be inſiſted on, would be a vaſt thing; I proceed therefore to temporals, and ſhall conſider what great things God hath wrought in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for temporall things, there is abundant matter of wonder in them: He is wonderfull in his protection and preſervation of his people; the Church may alwayes fing the 124. Pſalme, If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide. &amp;c. they had ſwallowed us up quick, &amp;c. for a company of Sheep and Lambs to live in the midſt of whole Heards and Droves of Wolves and Tygers, and all ſorts of Beaſts of prey is much; for the Buſh to burn, and not to be conſumed; for the veſſell of the Church to be full of waves ſometimes, and not to be drowned; for the male child newly borne to be kept from the Dragon with ſeven heads and ten hornes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. 3, 4. that the Lilly ſhould live in the midſt of Thornes, and not be torne in pieces; that the people of God ſhould be ſafe in the midſt of principalities and powers, and ſpirituall wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes, which bring out all their traine of Artilery, that come furniſhed with all the ammunition and magazine of hell: This is wonderfull preſervation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is wonderfull in his ſalvation and deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his people out of the greateſt dangers and out of many deaths; when God delivered his people from the power of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> then <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Song, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 11. ſay, <hi>Who is</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113723:6"/> 
               <hi>a God like unto thee, &amp;c. working wonders?</hi> When the people of God were delivered out of captivity, they were like men in a dream, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. 1. nay, the heathen themſelves ſaid, the Lord hath done great things for them, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he is wonderfull in the deſtruction that he brings by them on their enemies, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 41. 14. 15, 16. that a worm ſhould be as a new threſhing inſtrument to threſh the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, and beat them ſmall, and fan them, &amp;c. is a wonder: that <hi>Iſrael</hi> a poore contemned people, ſhould be the battle-axe of God, and his weapons of warre, to break in pieces the Nations, and to deſtroy Kingdomes, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 20, 21. this is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull; that a poore captivated people, even <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and undone, ſhould be a cup of trembling to all round about, and a burthenſome ſtone for all people, and cut them in pieces, &amp;c. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 2, 3, 6. that the ſtone cut out of the mountaine without hands, ſhould break in pieces the iron the braſſe, the clay, the ſilver and the gold, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 45. In this reſpect it may be ſaid, and it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he is wonderfull in his proviſion for them: It is the lot of the people of God to be driven into great ſtreights and extremities, as the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in the Wilderneſſe; yet as God did ſtill provide a ſupply for them, ſo he will alſo for his people, Iſa. 41. 17, 18, 20. <hi>When the poore and needy ſeeke water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirſt, I the Lord will heare them, &amp;c. I will open Rivers in high places, &amp;c.</hi> and Pſal. 34. 10. <hi>The young Lyons doe lacke, and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things which God works in his owne wonderfull way, they are ſuch, firſt, as nature never doth; or ſecondly, he doth work them ſo as that they are not brought to paſſe in the order and method of nature; or thirdly, not by the principles of nature; now they are ſaid to be <hi>miracula quod ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perent captum ingenii, ac homini incutiunt ſtuporem,</hi> Funger. Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mol. Latin. grae.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing propounded was, How the Lord would <note place="margin">2. How will, or how hath the Lord wrought theſe wonders?</note> work wonderfull things for his people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when contraries are made to produce effects oppoſite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113723:7"/> to themſelves: As when out of the greateſt diſadvantages he <note place="margin">1. When con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce effects oppoſite to themſelves: This is three wayes.</note> works the greateſt advantage; out of greateſt loſſes he extracts the greateſt gains, out of ruines he works a reparation: When God ſuffers his people to be beaten into victories, and routed into triumphs, and undone into riches, ſo that it may be ſaid many times <hi>periiſſent, niſi periiſſent:</hi> this is done, firſt, when he works on the affections, when he carries them againſt their owne ſtreame and tide, turnes curſes into bleſſings, as in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> caſe, and hatred into favour, and malignity into mercy, and ſpite into love, as he did in <hi>Laban</hi> toward <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 30. 24. and in <hi>Eſau,</hi> Gen. 33. 6. and in <hi>Abimelech</hi> toward <hi>Abraham</hi> Gen. 20. 14, 15, 16. Theſe however they were as Wolves in their purpoſes and reſolutions, yet the iſſues were moſt like Lambes. This is wonderfull, and we may ſay, Who is a God like unto thee, that canſt thus work?</p>
            <p>Secondly, when God turnes wiſdome into folly, that there ſhould be the wiſeſt Counſels, and the moſt fooliſh reſults and iſſues, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 1, 2, &amp;c. by making the wiſeſt men give the advice of fools, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 14. the wiſdome of the wiſe ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſh, &amp;c. and <hi>Joh</hi> 12. 16, 17. <hi>He leads Counſellours away ſpoyled, and maketh the Judges fooles;</hi> or, when he makes uſe of ſuch as are accounted fools to confound the wiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27. then it may be ſaid, Who is a God like unto thee?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when weakneſſe produceth ſtrong effects, then it may be ſaid, the Lord works wonderfully, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27. we have an inſtance, <hi>Judges</hi> 7. 20. and <hi>Joſhua</hi> 4. 20. that the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Rams hornes, like ſo many Rams againſt the wals of <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſhould batter them downe, that <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour-bearer ſhould rout an Army, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. that <hi>Shamgar</hi> with an Oxe Goad ſhould ſlay ſix hundred men, <hi>Judges</hi> 3. 31 that <hi>Sampſon</hi> with the Jaw-bone of an Aſſe ſhould ſlay a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, <hi>Judges</hi> 15. 16. that <hi>David,</hi> a puny, ſhould encounter with, and conquer <hi>Goliah,</hi> a man of war armed, with a ſtone in a ſling, is wonderfull; or elſe, when ſtrong and probable <note place="margin">2. When there be great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeintments of great hope: and this is done four wayes.</note> cauſes produce weak effects; as if a mighty Army ſhould come againſt a ſmall weak City, and not be able to take it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>2. When there be ſtrange fruſtrations of very great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113723:7"/> firſt, when a deſigne is built on power and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and carried on with skill and dexterity, then there be great hopes; now to have ſuch teeming hopes ſtrangled in the birth, or even when they are betwixt the womb and the world, is matter of very great wonder; not to obtaine where there is great probability, a bare diſappointment in ſuch a caſe is much; for the wit of hell to be puzzelled, and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſſed, for the power of men and devils, to be confounded in their full carreer; when they are riding poſt, for their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot wheels then to then to be taken off when they run moſt ſmoothly and ſwiftly, this is a great diſappointment; <note n="a" place="margin">—<hi>Recoctus ſcriba ex quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quevivo corvu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deluſit hia item</hi>
               </note> to fruſtrate a man when he is with open mouth ready to take in a prey, or even to fetch it out from between his <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bolus creptus faucibus, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cior</hi> ſaid <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (in ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum excru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciante) bolum tantum eſt mihi eſſe creptum a faucibus.</hi>
               </note> teeth, as it is <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 12. as the Shepheard taketh out of the mouth of the Lyon two legs, or a piece of an eare, &amp;c. this is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fruſtration: nay, when they have ſwallowed downe the prey, and it is now under the ſecond concoction, then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint them is more ſtrange, <hi>Job</hi> 20. 15. <hi>He hath ſwallowed downe riches, and he ſhall vomit them up againe:</hi> when the wicked have eaten and devoured the Saints, and as the Whale did by <hi>Jonah,</hi> ſwallow them downe alſo, ſo that they ſeem to be dead and buried, and the <hi>conclamatum eſt</hi> hath paſſed upon them, and no returning or recovery <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as one in <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> ſpeaks of one paſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and as <hi>Lucretius</hi> l. 3. expreſſeth it; <hi>Mortalem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam mars cui immortalis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demit.</hi>
               </note> lookt for, yet then to make theſe Whales to caſt up all their <hi>Jonahs</hi> and to land them ſafe, for theſe that were dead and buried to riſe againe, is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſappointment, and a wonderfull and aſtoniſhing thing, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 7, 8, 9,-11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there be great diſappointments, when expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are made ones deſtruction, when hopes fall on the authors head and daſh his braines out, when one is not onely diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the good that he lookt for from the child of his hopes, of which he travelled, but this child, like <hi>Adramelech</hi> and <hi>Sharezer,</hi> ſonnes to <hi>Senacharib,</hi> kill their father that begat them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 37, 38. We read of the wicked, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 16. how they are called Hunters and Fiſhers, becauſe they hunt and fiſh, and perſecute the people of God; now that theſe hunters ſhould be taken in their owne toyles, and theſe fiſhers ſhould be caught by their owne Angles, hanged on their own hooks,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113723:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113723:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113723:9"/> tangled in their owne Nets, is wonderfull: We have many inſtances, <hi>Judges</hi> 5. 28, 29, 30. how full of hopes was the Mother of <hi>Siſera</hi> and the reſt with her, and yet what ruine followed, even by them which they had ſwallowed up in their purpoſes and expectations, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 9. the enemy ſaid, <hi>I will purſue, I will overtake, I will divide the ſpoyle, my luſt ſhall be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them, I will destroy them:</hi> And yet all fell out not onely <hi>praeter ſpem,</hi> but <hi>contra,</hi> as much as could be: So, <hi>Judges</hi> 7. 22. &amp; 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 20. &amp; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 22, 23. they that brought weapons of cruelty to deſtroy the people of God, are ſo farre from doing them any hurt, that they kill and deſtroy one another: How was <hi>Haman</hi> and the enemies of <hi>Daniel</hi> diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and by their owne plots ruined, <hi>Heſter.</hi> 8. &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 24. thus doth God take the wicked in their owne craft, <hi>Job</hi> 5. 12, 13, 14, 15. and he that digs a pit for another, is buried in his owne grave, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 15, 16. which is matter of great wonder, and to which <hi>David</hi> affixeth, <hi>Higgaion Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, when there be ſtrange diſcoveries beyond all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability or expectation, when plots ſecretly and wiſely conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and managed, and almoſt ripe for an iſſve, it is a great diſappointment, then in that nick of time, to be diſcovered: As it fared with that <hi>monstrum horrendum, informe, ingens</hi> (and when fire was ready to be given, the match and powder were now meeting) <hi>cui lumen ademptum:</hi> I need not tell what I mean, every one knowes the Powder-treaſon to be even as the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne of Hell and <hi>Rome</hi> together: How did the Lord diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Counſels of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> when they were ready for execution, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 9. And how did the Lord diſcover that plot againſt the death of <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 23. 14, 15, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when counſels and deſignes in their proſecution running in a full ſtreame, have been turned cleane another way, by ſome unlookt for emergency, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 26, 27, 28. <hi>Saul</hi> in a hot purſuance of <hi>David,</hi> is taken off by a meſſenger that came and told him, the <hi>Philiſtians</hi> had invaded the Land: by this meanes very often it is, that the wicked are a ranſome for the righteous, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 18. <note place="margin">3. The third way which God takes to work wonders for his people</note>
            </p>
            <p>A third way that God takes to work theſe great things, is when by himſelf or by ſome of his creatures, he brings ſtrange
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113723:9"/> confuſion on his adverſaries, and ſtrange deliverance for his people: How did the Lord with a mighty hand deliver the people of Iſrael out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and with a mighty hand deſtroy their enemies, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7, 8, 9. chap. &amp; 15. 10. the Lord did blow with his wind, and the waters covered them; ſo when with his Angel he deſtroyed in a night one hundred forty five thouſand men: he delivered <hi>Eliſha, 2 Kings</hi> 6. 18, 19. by ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the enemy with blindneſſe; he withered <hi>Jeroboams</hi> hand, ſtretched out againſt the Prophet, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 4. God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time doth let forth ſome viſible demonſtrations of his wrath againſt his enemies, ſo that it may he truly ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> How did God ſmite <hi>Arrius?</hi> how did God take vengeance on him,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Arrius <hi>in foelix, qui curva per avia rectum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>flectere viſus iter, foveam delapſus in atram,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Corruit, &amp; tetri merſus petit ima profundi:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>tam vacuus ſenſu, justae quam tempore poenae</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Viſceribus fuſis vacuus quoque ventre remanſit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caelius Sidulius.</hi>—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Vid. Paurentii Pudovici, Orat. 1. eccleſ. vet. nov.</p>
                  <p>Vid. Franciſc. Baldwinum Jctum,</p>
                  <p>De Conſtantini Imp. legibus ecclefiaſt. atque civil, l. 1.</p>
                  <p>Camerar. Cent. 3. c. 3. Nathan Chytraeus in viatico itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris extemi.</p>
               </note> cauſing a ſudden conſternation of mind to fall upon him, who betaking himſelfe to a Privy, did emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty his bowels there? the death of <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> was moſt eminent from Gods hand immediately; the death of that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick <hi>Olympius</hi> was remarkable at that time, when he vented his herefie againſt the Trinity, he was ſmitten with fiery darts from heaven; and <hi>Anastaſius</hi> the Emperour, when he would needs have a quaternity worſhipped, was ſtruck with a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt from heaven; ſo that in this reſpect alſo we may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> I might be large in inſtances out of Eccleſiaſticall ſtory, but I forbeare.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113723:10"/>
            <p>Fourthly, when the Lord doth ſeem to alter and overthrow the courſe of nature in the deliverance of his people, and the ruine of their enemies: It is obſerved by <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid more Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vech.</hi> p. 2. c. 29</note> 
               <hi>R. Moſes Maiemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> that the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> when he ſpeaks of the deſtruction of a people, and the deliverance of his Church, he makes uſe of expreſſions of wouder and aſtoniſhment; as of the falling of ſtarres, the periſhing of the heavens, the darkning of the Sun, the devaſtation of the earth, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 10, 13. prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying of the ruine of <hi>Babel,</hi> he uſeth ſuch expreſſions of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24. 23. propheſying of the ruine of <hi>Sennacharib,</hi> he ſayes the like; both theſe were inveterate enemies of the Church: So alſo he ſpeaks of the reſcue and deliverance of the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 26. &amp; 34. 3, 4. ſpeaking of the ruine of <hi>Edom,</hi> which had long afflicted the people of God, and ſo would prove ſafety and deliverance unto them, he uſeth words of terrour and wonder: <hi>All the hoſt of heaven ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and the heavens ſhall be rolled together as a ſcroll, and all their hoſt ſhall fall downe as the leafe falleth off from the Vine, and as a falling fig from the Fig-tree:</hi> ſo alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 6. he ſpeaks his conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here, with chiding them for forgetting him that had made the heavens and earth, &amp;c. then <hi>ver.</hi> 16. when he ſpeaks of what great things he would doe for <hi>Zion,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>That he will plant the heavens, and lay the foundations of the earth, and ſay to</hi> Zion, <hi>Thou art my people.</hi> We read the like expreſſions elſwhere as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 20. 65. 17. &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32. 7. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 11,-30. In theſe and the like places the Lord uſeth ſuch expreſſions and words, as if he would alter and overturn the whole frame of the Univerſe, and begin the world anew, when he purpoſeth to doe great things for his people: We read of very ſtrange and prodigious things in the Roman ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſcattered up and downe, which God wrought, then eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when he had a purpoſe to bring ſome notable confuſion on the enemies of Gods people; there be <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Julius obſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qutus de prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris Polydore,</hi> Virgill. 3. <hi>de Prodigiis,</hi> ſpeaks of theſe prodigies with ſomcuſe to the Church.</note> divers that have taken paines to ſet downe theſe wonders, but without any reſpect to the mind of God in them with reference to his Church; yet <hi>Joſephus</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Joſephus l. 7 c. 82. <hi>De bello Judaico,</hi> he complaines of the great neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of theſe ſtrange things which God wrought, for ſayes he, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the wonders, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo tels us of a ſtrange appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition in the Heavens ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parebus,</hi> who lived toward the end of the Grecian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, about 120. yeers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt: Which prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſtar then appearing, did by the conſent of the learned foreſhew the declining of the Greek Monarchy, and the riſe and ſtrength of the Roman Empire.</note> hath taken notice of many ſignes in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113723:10"/> the heavens and earth before the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> one of the moſt famous alterations in the Heavens w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath had its moſt remarkable influences below, was in the yeer 1572. when there appeared a ſtrange light, exceeding in the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent brightneſſe thereof all the fixed ſtars, and ſhewing forth a bright and majeſticall luſtre, not in the night onely, but at noon day alſo: It was the wonder of the world, and the work and buſineſſe of all the Aſtronomers of <hi>Europe;</hi> but <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho Brahe</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Denmark</hi> treateth of this ſtarre in above 500. pages of his book, called by the name of <hi>Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica Progymnaſmata:</hi> In which book he ſpeakes of the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of this ſtar, and the overthtow of States and Kingdoms, and reparation and glory of the Church: I make mention of theſe onely to ſhew how the Lord doth great things, even overthrowing or changing and altering the frame and courſe of nature: As for the operations or portending ſignification of ſuperiour lights, I think it cannot be denied, but that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary wonders viſible in the heavens may have their ſignifications and impreſſions alſo: nor may it be altogether incongruous literally to interpret thoſe words, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 30. <hi>I will ſhew wonders in the heavens and the earth,</hi> partly of that fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword, like the Comet <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Egeſip. de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid. urbis Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſol.</hi> l. 5. c. 44. <hi>Nam per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num fere ſupra templum ipſum Comites, paſſim ignis &amp; gladii quandam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferens ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem denunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abat quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ferra &amp; igni gentis &amp; regni urbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſius vastita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem futuram: quid enim ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudo gladii niſi bellum? quid ignis niſi incendium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciaret.</hi> The third thing propoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and time when it ſhall be ſaid, What God wrought?</note> that appeared as a forewarner of the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing propounded was, when it ſhall be ſaid <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> for the time:</p>
            <p>When creature helps faile; firſt, in point of prudence they know not how to adviſe: ſecondly, in point of power, they know not how to deliver or ſave, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 35, 36. thirdly, in occaſionall emergent difficulties, ſuch as could neither be foreſeen nor prevented: fourthly, in great extremities and ſtreights, when enemies are very high and the Saints are very low; when heaven and earth and hell ſeem to joyne iſſue, when God himſelfe ſeemes to take part againſt the Church, then ſhe is in the greateſt extremity, ahd when ſhe is in this caſe, then doth God ariſe and help her.</p>
            <p>Indeed Gods ſeaſon is, when it ſeems to be paſt ſeaſon, his time is when it is paſt time, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. when the people of God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113723:11"/> are in a forlorne condition, given up for loſt, then God, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. ſayes, <hi>Now will I ariſe, now will I he exalted, now will I lift up my ſelfe:</hi> Now, now, now, he repeats it three times with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of language, there is ſomething more then ordinary in that expreſſion, ſo trebled as it is, to encourage their ſinking ſouls, who thought God would not, or could not, or had alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether laid aſide the thoughts and care of helping them; when the wound is paſt cure, then he undertakes the cure, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 12, 13. there it is ſaid, <hi>Thy wound is incurable,</hi> and ver. 17. It is ſaid, <hi>I will cure thee:</hi> When all paſſages are blockt up, when there is a cloſe ſiege of difficulties and impoſſibilities, when dangers are inextricable, and the matter paſt recovery, then is Gods time; when the ſhip is full of waves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 24. when <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead and buried, <hi>John</hi> 11. 21, 32, 39. when the woman had ſpent all ſhe had upon Phyſitians, and there was as little hope as mony left, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 43. then is the Lords time to work and fetch out of the fire as it were, <hi>Zech.</hi> 3. 2. and from the dead, <hi>Revol.</hi> 11. 11. and from the ruines and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of death, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. 7, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing propounded was, why doth God thus <note place="margin">The fourth Particular pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded, was concerning the reaſon, why doth God thus appeare in ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for his people. The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reſpects Gods glory.</note> appeare for his people; firſt, to magnifie his owne glory more; the firſt end reſpects Gods glory: there be three things in the wonderfull proceedings of God that magnifie him very much: Firſt, there is a myſtery in the proceedings of God; myſteries affect with wonder and admiration, and the Lord doth carry on his work in a very myſterious way, and in a hidden manner: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 15. it is ſaid, <hi>Thou art a God which hideſt thy ſelfe,</hi> ſpoken with reference to the great things which he would doe for his people: ſo alſo, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>He had hornes came out of his hand, and there was the hiding of his power:</hi> there be many intricacies of providence, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. 16. and perplexed and involved difficulties; ſo <hi>Zech.</hi> 1. 8. the Lord Chriſt is in that viſion preſented in a Wood, and in a bottome, not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned, when he comes to work for his people; myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe affect with wonder more, and they magnifie the Lord more.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a majeſty in theſe wonders, and this doth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113723:11"/> cauſe men to admire alſo &amp; to magnifie the Lord; he ſeems to goe in ſtate as it were, when he will doe great things for his people, <hi>Deut. 33. 26. The Lord rideth on the heavens for thy help, and his excellency on the skie:</hi> ſo <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 8, 9. the Lord appeares in his Majeſty there, and <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, the Sun and other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſeem to be trembling and wondring; and <hi>Nahum</hi> 1. 3, 4. the Lord is brought in, in a glorious manner; and then, <hi>ver. 5. The mountaines quake, &amp;c.</hi> this alſo doth magnifie the Lord, and ſhew forth his glory.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is a peculiar excellency in Gods great workes which doth affect the heart with wonder; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his wiſdome ſhewes it ſelfe in infatuating and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the councels of the wiſe, and of his power that ſhines in breaking their ſtrength, in which the wicked are ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; the excellency of his juſtice that appeares in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wicked, and vindication of his peoples cauſe; the excellency of his faithfulneſſe and truth breaks out in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good his Word, and fulfilling his promiſes. This is the firſt reaſon why God doth work wonders for his, in which there is a myſtery, a majeſty, and a peculiar excellency ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing reſpects the enemies of Gods people; firſt, <note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies of the Saints two wayes. 1. That the confuſion of the enemies might be the more notable.</note> that ſo the greater confuſion and ſhame may come on the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Saints; for God to deliver his Saints from many, and mighty, and malicious enemies is a wonder, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it is with great confuſion on the adverſaries. There is by ſo much the greater confuſion on the wicked, by how much the more ſure they made themſelves of the ruine of Gods people, and by how much the more the enemy was exalted, as it is <hi>Obad.</hi> 3. 4. the Lord orders it ſo in his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the confuſion and ſhame of the wicked ſhall have all the ingredients in it, that ſo the wonder may be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: firſt, they ſhall conceive great hopes of accompliſhing their deſignes. Secondly, they ſhall carry on thoſe hopes with much ſucceſſe even almoſt to a deſired iſſue; they ſhall plow, and ſowe, and be ready to reape. Thirdly, there ſhall be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment ſudden, unexpected, unavoidable, irrecoverable.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113723:12"/> Fourthly, that which they leaſt of all looked for ſhall come to paſſe, even that themſelves ſhould be deſtroyed by them whom they thought to deſtroy, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 2, 3. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is a cup of trembling, ſhe that was rather as a cup of wine that might invite an adverſary to drinke it up, for ſweet wine being in a cup tempts more then being in a Butt or Barrel, and is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being ſwallowed downe; now that this cup which is ſo expoſed to every one that goes by, ſhould be a cup of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ruine to them that thought to devoure it, carries much ſhame and confuſion. It is ſaid that it ſhall be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome ſtone; it is not ſaid it ſhall be as a milſtone, or a mountain to cruſh in peeces, for if the Church were of a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bulke and greatneſſe able to make its part good with an adverſary, then perhaps they would not be ſo eager againſt it. There is no man going by a ſtone of many loads and of a mighty weight will attempt to remove it, but a little ſtone that lyes in ones way that may be ſpurn'd w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the foot, or take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up in the hand &amp; caſt away: a ſtone, firſt, that is little; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that lyes ready in the way to be caſt aſide, or made uſe of. Thirdly, in which is a fitneſſe for uſe to ones ſelfe; ſuch a ſtone carries a kinde of temptation with it to one to carry it away; ſuch a ſtone the Church ſeemes to be in the eyes of her enemies; the Church of God lyes in the way of wicked men, as a little contemptible ſtone that they need not take much pains withall, but ſuch as they may kick out of the way with the foot, or eaſily caſt it away with their hand; now that this ſtone ſhould be like many milſtones and mountains to daſh the wicked in peeces, that is the greater confuſion and ſhame.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reſpect is in regard of the great terrour, as well as <note place="margin">2. That there might be the greater terror brought on the wicked.</note> the great ſhame which God bringeth on the wicked, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 14, 15, 16. when God had wrought that wonderfull delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for his people, and confuſion of their adverſaries, the enemies round about were afraid; ſo it was alſo <hi>Joſh</hi> 2. 9, 10, 11. &amp; 5. 1. &amp; <hi>Deut.</hi> 2. 25. &amp; <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. 2, 3, 6. <note place="margin">The third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reſpects the people of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third reaſon why God will worke ſtrange things for his people againſt their enemies, reſpects the people of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113723:12"/> God themſelves; that they might appeare the more glorious, and be knowne to be ſaved by the Lord, <hi>Deut. 33. 29. Happy art thou O Iſrel, who is like unto thee? ſaved by the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 2. <hi>Sam. 7. 23. What one Nation in the earth is like thy people, even like Iſrael, whom God went out to redeem from a people to himſelfe, and to make him a name, and to doe for you great things and terrible? &amp;c.</hi> this was it which did make the people of God ſo famous and glorious that God had done ſuch wonders for them.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall proced to uſe, firſt, of caution: God hath <note place="margin">The fift parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular propoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded was, what uſe may be made of this which hath bin ſpoken of theſe wonders of the Lord. The firſt Uſe is a Uſe of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> wrought great things for you: (Honourable and beloved) take heed leaſt by your ingratitude, you cauſe him to doe great things againſt you: It hath been ſaid, what hath God wrought for you? beware that it be not ſaid, what hath God wrought againſt you? he hath made you the wonders of his mercy, take heed that he doth not make you the wonders of his fury: It hath been ſaid, what hath God wrought, that hath magnified his wiſdome in carrying on your affaires; take heed he doth not leave you to your ſelves, and ſo you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the wonders of folly and madneſſe to all the world; he hath magnified his power in your behalfe, take heed he doth not diſmantle you, and lay you naked, and make you won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of weakneſſe, and expoſe you as a prey to the moſt contemptible enemy: he hath made you the wonders of his protection and love, take heed he doth not make you the wonders of his rejection, as it was with Iſrael.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe a caveat now cannot be thought unſeaſonable, in regard I find that the greateſt temporall mercies which ever God gave to his people, were given with the greateſt caveats and many proviſoe's, they were given under lock and key as it were, a mercy and a caution, as a keeper to goe along with it to ſee to the good behaviour of him that hath it in the uſe of it: The Lord did nurture the Iſraelites, being to enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and he did diſcipline them beforehand, and give them many caveats, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 1, 2. there is an exhortation to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being to enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; ver. 5, 6. ſpeaking of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thither, <hi>take heed therefore,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. &amp; 14, 15, 16. he ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, &amp; <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. &amp; 38, 29, 40.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113723:13"/> 
               <hi>take heed, &amp;c.</hi> then againe, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. 10, 11, 12. ſpeaking of the plenty of <hi>Canaan, then beware,</hi> ſayes he to them; and <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 10, 11. <hi>take heed,</hi> againe: <hi>David</hi> gives <hi>Solomon</hi> (ſpeaking of great things that he ſhould enjoy) warning to beware; and Chriſt ſaid to him that he healed, <hi>John 5. 14. Sin no more, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there is great reaſon of this, becauſe upon the receipt of great mercies, we are in danger of great ſins: we find that they which have been the wonders of the world in regard of great favours from God, have been the wonders of the world after, for great ſins againſt God: <hi>Noah</hi> had the favour to be preſerved in the Arke from that univerſall deluge when the world was drowned, and <hi>Noah</hi> not long after was drowned in drunkenneſſe. <hi>Lot</hi> had that great mercy ſhewed him to be delivered out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and after! that he turned <hi>Zoar</hi> into a <hi>Sodom</hi> by his uncleanneſſe: How ſhamefully did <hi>David</hi> fall, after thoſe multitude of favours he had from God 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 7, 8, 9. How did <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſhew himſelfe to be very unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, after ſuch mercies as all the world might wonder at: How did <hi>Jonah</hi> qvarrell with God preſently after after he came out of the Whales belly: How did <hi>Peter</hi> deny his Maſter with an oath, that had the honour (beſides other favours) to ſee him transfigured in the mount? We are in danger, firſt, <note n="a" place="margin">It is reported of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> that he appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a Lad to come to him every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before any other, and ſay to him three times, <hi>Philipe homo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> leaſt upon the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories over the Athenians he might for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get himſelfe, <hi>Aelian. variar. Histo.</hi> l. 8. c. 15 that of <hi>Tacitus</hi> is ſure, <hi>acrius explorant ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum resproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae quam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſae,</hi> Terrul. in Apologet. Arrian, l. 3.</note> of pride, of being lifted up above our ſelves: It was the ſin of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> 2 Chron. 26. 16. when he waxed ſtrong his heart was lifted up: ſecondly, we be in danger of forgetfulneſſe, <hi>Dent.</hi> 8. 16. thirdly, <note n="b" place="margin">They that write of the ruine of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, do give this as on cauſ &amp; that a chief one, <hi>to wit,</hi> proſperity <hi>Althus. Polit.</hi> l. 23. c. 7. <hi>Val. max.</hi> l. 7. c. 2. <hi>Alex. ab Alex.</hi> l. 3. c. 20. <hi>lipſ.</hi> lib. 6. and the Scripture is frequent and full in this particular.</note> we are in danger of luxury and riot, we quickly ſurfet and wax wanton with mercies: fourthly, of careleſneſſe, you need not adviſe one that is poore or ready to be ſtaryed, to look out for proviſion, ſuch will be too care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but you had need adviſe them that are rich and full, leaſt they grow negligent and ſupine, and careleſſe in their duty to God, and laying out what they have for his glory: fiftly, we are in danger of relapſes, after recovery out of great dangers and diſeaſes, &amp;c. if there be not great care, we fall into the old trade and way againe, daily experience teſtifies this truth: ſixtly, we are in danger of great judgements, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 13, 14. in all theſe reſpects, we have a much more ſlippery ſtanding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113723:13"/> then we had before: A Paradiſe is a much more dangerous place for us to be in then a Wilderneſſe.</p>
            <p>But what muſt we beware of chiefly: Firſt, that we doe not forget our low eſtate before God wrought theſe wonders for us: For this conſideration doth much advance Gods won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by how much the lower our ſtate &amp; condition was, when he began to work for us, by ſo much the greater is the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and therefore God will not have us forget our low eſtate. The Lord doth very often make mention of the deliverance he wrought for Iſrael, and he makes expreſſe mention of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and the houſe of bondage; he ſpeaks of it, firſt, in giving of the Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 1. ſecondly, when he inſtituted the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, <hi>Levit.</hi> 22. 33. thirdly, when he makes the promiſe of bleſſings to them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 13. fourthly, in reckoning up his great works he had done for them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 32, 33, 34. and when he ſpeaks of the favours he would beſtow, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 10, 11, 12. fiftly, he reckons it as a great ſigne of his love, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 8. ſixtly, when he diſſwades them from ingratitude, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 14. ſeventhly, when he inſtituted the paſchall Lamb, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 6. eightly, when the Angel reproved the people, <hi>Judges</hi> 2. 1. ninthly, when he purpoſed to give them victory over the Midianites, <hi>Judges</hi> 6. 8, 9, 10, &amp;c. tenthly, when they were about to ſet up a King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 18. how frequent is the Lord in making mention of <hi>Aegypt</hi> upon every occaſion? ſurely to put them in mind of their low eſtate, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 5. the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is bid to remember from whence ſhe was fallen; and ſurely we muſt not forget from whence we are riſen, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 6, 7. that it may with greater wonder be ſaid, What hath God wrought for us that were ſo low? for God himſelfe takes occaſion to amplifie his favours upon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 3, 4, 5. ſo <hi>David</hi> reckons it among the miracles of mercies, that God remembred them in their low eſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. 23. we muſt not forget who they were that owned us and the cauſe we undertook, in our low eſtate: It was confeſſed that our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> did ſuch ſervice for us, that they deſerved much at our hands, as much at leaſt as <note n="a" place="margin">In his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intituled <hi>New Englands ſence of old England and Irelands ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</hi>
               </note> Maſter <hi>Hooke</hi> in his Sermon gives them, when he ſtiles
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113723:14"/> them, that honourable Nation that united in a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant againſt the Prelats; we may have cauſe enough to think on them, as Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> doth in his Sermons on the Vials, where he apprehends that God made uſe of them to poure out his Viall upon the ſeat of the Beaſt, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he thinks that the word there cleerly point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> 5. Vial</note> Scots: Of whom he ſayes; <hi>Nor doe I know that any of the former Vyals have been poured out by any men, whoſe loynes have been more girt about with truth, and whoſe cloathing hath been more pure and white, then theſe ſervants of God have been girt with, and cloathed withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. We muſt beware we doe not forget the ſpeciall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God which goe along with his great mercies, for theſe doe put a very great price upon the favours you receive: God ſends you a Cabinet in ſuch a mercy, you muſt open it, and you ſhall find many jewels in it: he doth diſmember a mercy that doth not take it in all its dimenſions, nor can God have the full praiſe of a compleat mercy, when we our ſelves doe not ſee into all the parts of it; we muſt therefore look at the mercy, and, Firſt, the ſeaſon of the mercy, in the Mount; extremity was Gods opportunity; when thy ſpirit would have failed, if God had not then come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 16. then to afford mercy, when the full time to have mercy was come, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 11. is a bleſſed fit time; or perhaps it was at ſuch a ſeaſon, when we were praying and faſting, or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after; God is pleaſed to time his mercies which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes; for it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa. 49. 8. In an acceptable time have I heard thee;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſayes, <hi>Pſal. 69. 13. In an acceptable time have I prayed;</hi> it is a bleſſed ſeaſon for God to be giving when we are praying, as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 24. <hi>Whilſt they are ſpeaking, I will heare:</hi> How oft have our Thankſgiving dayes trod on the heels of our Faſting dayes? how oft have Victories come flying on the wings of prayer ſo faſt, that they have taken us upon our knees?</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt not forget the many difficulties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies through which our mercies have been conveyed to us; we muſt look at the croſſe, perplexed paſſages of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113723:14"/> there hath been many a time in our great affaires, an appearance, as it were a wheels within a wheele, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. 16. ſo that God manifeſted his mervailous loving kindneſſe, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. 7. when he hath given a bleſſed iſſue in ſuch caſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we muſt not forget this providence, when God makes many meanes conſpire for our good, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a conſtellation of means of different complexions to coutribute their influences for our good; when men of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary temper and diſpoſition one from another and averſe from me, ſhould yet be overſwayed to combine for my good, this is an admirable providence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt not forget how ſuddenly and unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly the Lord hath done things for us: The Lord hath not wearied us out with waiting; that which lookt like a work of two ſeven yeers, he hath diſpatched in the ſpace of two ſeven moneths; many a victory hath come ſo ſuddenly, that it hath even ſurprized us, that we have been as men in a dreame, as the children of the captivity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, we muſt not forget the fruitfulneſſe of our mercies; one mercy hath been pregnant and big with child with many: our victories carry in their wombe, our lives, our liberties, our intereſts and priviledges, our Goſpel and Reformation; none of which we ſhould enjoy, if ſo be the enemy had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered: God hath given us many mother mercies.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, the ſmall loſſe of blood and men, this muſt not be forgotten; we might have purchaſed many things at a deare rate; if theſe victories and ſurrenders had come ſwimming in blood, or if there had been the demoliſhing Cities, Univerſity and Townes, we might have wept over our victories, as the children of Iſrael did when they had conquered their Brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> Judg. 20. 2.</p>
            <p>Perhaps thoſe that have been engaged in theſe tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whom God hath made inſtrumentall in his ſervice, are able to ſpeak of many particular experiments of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which we that are at a diſtance, are not able to diſcern: Let them whom it doth moſt concerne have a ſpeciall care
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113723:15"/> that God loſeth none of his honour in thoſe remarkable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of his providence towards them that have enjoyed them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we muſt not forget how we have provoked God, how we have murmured, how we have diſtruſted, how ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we have been lifted up with ſucceſſe, and then we thought we ſhould never be removed, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. 6, 7. and when the Lord hid his face, how were we troubled? ſometimes we have been in a full tide, and then againe at a dead low ebbe. This is it which the Lord preſſeth on his people, <hi>Deut. 9. 7. Remember and forget not how thou provokedſt the Lord thy God to wrath in the Wilderneſſe, from the day that thou depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedſt out of</hi> Aegypt <hi>untill ye came unto this place, ye have been a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt beware that we do not forget our Vows, Prayers, Faſts, Covenants, Proteſtations: The ſervants of God do drive a great trade with Heaven by theſe, they have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with God; we ſhould take notice of our revenues &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns hereby: now we are too apt to forget our engagements to the Lord; and hence it is that God preſſeth Covenant on his people when they ſhould come into <hi>Canaan,</hi> Deut. 4. 23. <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>leaſt ye forget the Covenant of the Lord your God &amp;c.</hi> remember, as it is, to offer unto God Thankſgiving, and pay thy Vowes to the moſt high; keep Covenant, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Vowes and Promiſes made with God, with your friends, with your enemies: It is a complaint (God grant it be not found to be true) that Articles are not kept on our part with the enemy; I ſhall onely mind you of that paſſage, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 9. how the Iſraelites did keep their Covenant with the Gibeonites, though they were undermined, and it were to their prejudice: <note n="a" place="margin">The formes of Covenants among the Romans and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were very ſtrict, and their obſervation of them alſo; after the invocation of their gods, they did bind themſelves under a curſe after this manner: <hi>Si prior de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecit</hi> (ſpeaking of the Pop. Rom.) <hi>publico conſilio, dolo malo tu illo die Jupiter Pop. Rom. ſic ferito, ut ego hunc porcum hodic feriam: tantoque magis ferito, quanto magis potes, polleſque: Id ubi dixit, porcum ſaxo ſilice percuſſit</hi> T. Liv l. 1. <hi>de faedere inter Tullum Hostilium &amp; Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos percuſſo agens.</hi> Vid. Barn. Briſſ. de form. l. 4.</note> The Heathens and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, &amp;c. have been moſt preciſe in this particular; now we ought to beware that we doe not forget all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113723:15"/> theſe conſiderations, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pauſanias in Arcadicis obſervavit, ubi ſcribit</hi> Philippi Macedonis <hi>Regis liberos propterea tantis calamitatibus affectos fuiſſae, quod ipſe fidem in pactis conventis, confae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratis datam, nihil faceret. Camerarius oper. ſubſic.</hi> l. 2. c. 78. How doth <hi>Agamemnon</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> cry out againſt the breach of faith in the Trojans. which he ſayes, God will avenge; whoſe ſenſe we have in theſe Verſes:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et ſuperiuros violato foedere Troas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jupitere Coelis praeſenti haud puniet ira,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At quandoque graves magno cum faenore poenas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hi cum coniugibus &amp; tota ſtirpe rependent.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>The very Heathen have ſet it as a brand on ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for breach of faith: Hence <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Tit. 1. 12. he cites <hi>Epimenides</hi> for this, who ſayes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. So <hi>dolus Troianus in Plauti Pſeudolo &amp; Punicaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>les,</hi> are taken up as Proverbs of reproach; ſo that this ſin had alwayes a note of ignominy among the Heathen. <hi>Grat. de iure belli,</hi> l. 2. c. 13.</p>
               </note> they all do add much to the wonder of Gods mercies: For firſt, may it not be truly ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> who hath raiſed us from ſo low a ſtate to this condition, that he ſhould be pleaſed to take notice of us, when none durſt owne us? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, may it not be ſaid <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> in al theſe admirable providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces afforded to us? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may it not be truly ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> who preſerved us when we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him? Fourthly, may it not be truly ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> who had reſpect to the prayers, faſts, &amp;c. of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervants? wherefore if we ſhould forget theſe, we ſhould much diſhonour God, and take off from the wonder of his mercies.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, we muſt beware that we doe not forget the low condition of others: It is a ſinne which thoſe that enjoy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall accommodations, are incident unto, even to forget others that are in want and miſery: You know how <hi>Ireland</hi> cryes aloud for help, and can find none; ſhall we think to ſit downe in peace, when <hi>Ireland</hi> is in blood, and even bleeding to death? We read <hi>Numb.</hi> 31. how the Iſraelites did give a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great overthrow to the Midianites, and what ſpoyle they took, and <hi>chap.</hi> 32. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. we read how the children of <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> having a great multitude of Cattle, therefore they deſired of <hi>Moſes</hi> that they might ſtay in that Country which the Lord had ſmote before the Congregation of Iſrael, it being a very commodious place: but <hi>ver. 6. Moſes</hi> ſaid to them that made this requeſt, <hi>ſhall your Brethren goe to warre, and ſhall yee ſit here, &amp;c.</hi> he chides them, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8, &amp;c. and tels them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113723:16"/> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 14. that <hi>they were riſen up in their Fathers ſtead, an encreaſe of ſinfull men, &amp;c.</hi> So ſay I, if we ſhall now ſit down and take up our reſt, and think our work is done, when <hi>Ireland</hi> hath no reſt, and is in a manner undone, this may provoke the Lord againſt us: I hope you will remember them in their low eſtate as God hath remembred you in yours.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe ſhall be of Exhortation, that ſince God hath wrought ſuch deliverances as theſe, and hath given ſuch wonderfull mercies to you, that you would labour to walke in a way correſpondent to theſe mercies, that you would be wrapt up with wonder in the contemplation of them; we may make uſe of the ſignification of the word <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari,</hi> and ſtirre you up to your duty, and goe no further then the Word affords: Firſt, it ſignifies <hi>intente intueri,</hi> for it comes from the Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>eſt viſus,</hi> ſo that we firſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: <note place="margin">Martin. Lexic. vocab. Miror.</note> Firſt, Take a view and ſurvey our mercies, look into them; this I have ſpoke of before: ſecondly, we ſhould <hi>mirari, (i.) cum voluptate intueri,</hi> we ſhould as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 13. 5, 6. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord, and ſing unto him, becauſe he hath dealt bountifully; we ſee the Church often upon the receipt of mercies, rejoycing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 10. and elſwhere: thirdly, we ſhould wonder <hi>(i.) Intueri cum ſtupore,</hi> break out into holy aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; the Church upon the contemplation of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, ſtands as one amazed, <hi>Iſa. 25. 9. In that day it ſhall be ſaid, Loe, this is our God!</hi> an <hi>ecce,</hi> a note of wonder put upon it; then it followes, We will rejoyce in his ſalvation: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we ſhould wonder and ſay, <hi>What hath God wrought! (i.) magnifacere &amp; venerari,</hi> we ſhould exalt and magnifie the Lord for his mercies; thus <hi>David</hi> teacheth us this leſſon in his owne practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 2, 3. he cals upon others to magnifie the Lord with him for his mercies: this magnifying of the Lord ſhould be done with holy and humble veneration: We find <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. 10, 11. when the four and twenty Elders give praiſe to God, they fall downe before him, and caſt their Crownes before the Throne, &amp;c. ſo alſo <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 8. &amp; 7. 11. &amp; 11. 16, 17. they fall downe and give thanks to the Lord God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had taken to him his great power, and had reigned;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113723:16"/> and <hi>chap.</hi> 19. upon the great judgement on the Whore, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. the four and twenty Elders and the four Beaſts fell down and worſhipped God that ſate on the Thronc, ſaying, <hi>Amen Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now propound ſome conſiderations to you, taken from ſome of the wonderfull things which God hath done for us, that by them I may raiſe up your hearts to the higheſt ſtraines of admiration and gratitude, and quicken you up to anſwerable walking, according to the great mercies of God beſtowed on us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it hath been ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> who hath brought this warre (in a manner) to an end, which every one almoſt did think would have ended our liberties, lives? &amp;c. now by way of gratitude, let us all labour to put an end to the warre, one among, and one againſt another: I could heartily wiſh that the Sea of Ordinances were Chryſtall, very pure, and not glaſſe, and freed from fire, that contentions were baniſhed from us, <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. 2. me thinks we ſhould not quarrell; that one word in which we all agree, <hi>viz.</hi> Saints, Brethrne, Members; nay that reconciling word, Chriſt, for we are one Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 12. I ſay, any of theſe words ſhould compoſe all differences among us; how often have ſome noble Commanders, by a word ſometimes, ſuch as that, <hi>commilitones, Quirites,</hi> ſetled the diſtempers of a mutinous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; why ſhould not that word Chriſtians, like that word <hi>Peace, be ſtill,</hi> ſpoken by Chriſt to the winds and waves when they were moſt boyſtrous, bring a great calme among us, as that did once? <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 39. The iſſue of our diviſions and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities is generally the ſame in effect as I have read in a ſtory concerning two Doctors of Phyſick, the one a Galeniſt, and the other a Paracelſian, who met at a feaſt, and fell into a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute: the Galeniſt diſcourſed of the retentive faculty in the ſtomack, how the meat is there depreſſed for a time, and made fit for digeſtion, and thence a milkie juyce is ſucked by the <hi>Meſaraicae venae,</hi> which forthwith is conveyed to the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of blood, thence to the heart the ſtore houſe of ſpirits, and ſo theſe two, like two carefull Purveyors, ſend their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113723:17"/> by the veynes and arteries, as by two common road wayes, into every part of the little Common-wealth of mans body: The Paracelſian, a profeſſor and practiſer quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the other, as well in his order of dyet as cure, oppoſeth himſelf againſt all theſe aſſertions, partly out of opinion that he was in the right, and partly out of a contentious humour and ſpleen which he bore to the others profeſſion; they fall from argument to railing, and at laſt to deadly war and bitter defiance, whereby the meale they then made was hindred in digeſtion, choler encreaſed in the one, and malancholy in the other, and the blood enflamed in both, ſo as they were both taken away (without ſaying grace) deſperately ſick; the Galeniſt of a ſhaking ague, and the Paracelſian of a dead pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: there needs no application, it is well knowne that the Galeniſt and Paracelſian men of contrary judgements, doe ſometime fall to diſputation, from this to railing, from this to diſtemper and ſickneſſe of ſpirit, by which meanes God loſeth the glory due to him, and many times both loſe both themſelves and the truth to boot: It is a ſad thing to me to think that they which look on one another as Saints, ſhould behave themſelves each to other as the Jewes had wont to doe toward Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>Hence we read of thoſe words in the new Teſt. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>alieni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis;</hi> ſo it is often objected by <hi>Joſephus</hi> againſt the Jewes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> whence that of <hi>Juvenal</hi> concerning the Jewes,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non monstrare vias, eadem niſi ſacra colenti,</hi> and that of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> Hiſt. 5. <hi>apud ipſos fides obſtinata, miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia in promptu adverſus omnes hoſtile odium:</hi> What a miſerable thing is it, that this Jewiſh carriage and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, theſe excommunicating termes ſhould be made good among thoſe that are received into the boſome of the ſame Chriſt? <hi>Althusius</hi> in his Politiques, c. 31. ſayes, <hi>Exitus diſcordiarum eſt, aut univerſorum interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, aut victoris dominatus &amp; regnum,</hi> vid. Bodin. l. 4. c. 1. there was a ſad iſſue of thoſe names of difference the Guelphs and the Gibbelines, the Calviniſts and Lutherans, the Samaritans and the Jewes; let us learne from them to lay aſide charactericing names, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe at length into factions and tumults.</p>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may be ſaid <hi>What hath God wrought</hi> for you in reſtoring your cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated liberties, your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalved priviledges, your lawes made arbitrary once by uſurpation and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of late by neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in time of warre: In a common fire and confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration, many houſes muſt be pluckt downe to ſave the reſt <note n="b" place="margin">H. Grotius, l. 3. de jure belli, c. 1.</note>; and many things
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113723:17"/> are lawfull in a time of warre, which otherwiſe could not be permitted: Since therefore God hath done this for you, let it by way of gratitude be ſaid, what hath this Parliament done, in labouring to ſettle the peace of the Church: He hath done your work very quickly; ſet cloſe to his and doe it quickly: or elſe you may have Chriſt come quickly as he threatned, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 5. and remove your Candleſtick from yo; and as it is <hi>ver. 16. Repent, or elſe I will come quickly and fight againſt thee, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Revel. 3. 11. Behold I come quickly, &amp;c.</hi> the adverſary makes haſte to pluck up, and to pull down and to unſettle the Church of God, and build up his own Babel of fancy and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and falſhood: whilſt the Ordinances of God are unſetled in their purity, power, glory and perfection, in their full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe and latitude, the enemy gets ground. Biſhop <hi>Jewell</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jewel</hi> in ep: de conc. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. tract. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de Papa &amp; Cardinal. &amp;c.</note> ſpeaking of the ſubtilty of the Pope and Cardinals, to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> or to retard it, makes uſe of a Story which may be applied to our caſe: It is reported of the Athenians, that when they began to build their wals which were caſt downe, the Lacedaemonians (that ſo they might have them in their power) ſent to them to ſurceaſe: But <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> being very wiſe, perceiving that the ſafety of the Country was in jeopardy, promiſed that he would come to them, yet he did purpoſely create delayes and excuſes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that their agreements did not like him, and then ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he would ſend Ambaſſadours to treat with them: In the meane time while he baffles them with delayes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, the building of the wals goes on, and in the time they are diſputing the matter, the buſineſſe is diſpatched, and the wals are built, and now pluck them downe that dare or can. It is certainly the deſigne of ſome to keep you off by delayes and plauſibilities and faire pretences, from ſetting in its full power the government of Chriſt, but in the meane time the wals of <hi>Athens</hi> goes on; and ere long, if you doe not make the more haſte, they will be finiſhed, and then you may pluck them downe if you could tell how: And as God hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered you from arbitrary government, ſo doe you leave as little to arbitrement in the State as can be: A good Law is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the beſt Lawyer <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Melius eſt legibus, ac con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinibus bonis ſidere, quam octimis hominibus</hi> Cardan. l. 5. de Sapient.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113723:18"/>
            <p>Thirdly, it may be ſaid <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> who hath ſubdued your enemies in the Field, many, mighty, malicious; who as they called you Rebels formerly, and think you ſo ſtill, ſo they would have uſed you as Rebels; by way of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude labour to ſubdue Gods enemies in your houſes and hearts, thoſe reigning ſinnes that captivate you, and ride in triumph over you. Is not that true which we read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 14. The ſonnes alſo of them that afflicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee, and all they that deſpiſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves downe at the ſoales of thy feet, &amp;c. how ſhould you ſtirre up your ſelves to mortifie your luſts? It was the glory of the King of <hi>Arragon</hi> that he conquered himſelfe when he conquered his enemies: And it was the blot on <hi>Alexanders</hi> conqueſts, that himſelfe was conquered with wine: and on <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that cruelty was his Maſter. We find in Stories ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcoffes of Souldiers caſt on their triumphing Commanders in this kind. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gallias Caeſar ſubegr, Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modes Caeſarem Ecce Caeſar nunc triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phat, qui ſubegit Gallias. Nicomodes non triumphat, qui ſubegit Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> Sueton in Jul. c. 49. and alſo c. 40. concerning the ſame, they that wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his triumph by way of mockery. <hi>U bani ſervate uxores, Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum calvum adducimus. Auro in Gallia ſtuprum emiſti, hic ſumpsiſti mutuum.</hi> So true is that diſtich. <hi>Fortior eſt qui ſe quam qui for tiſſima vincit Maenia, nec virtus altius ire poteſt.</hi>
               </note> Let us downe with the ſtrong holds of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. Ale-houſes generally are the Devils Caſtles, the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places of Malignants and Sectaries, they are the <hi>campus Martius</hi> of Satan, he hath his traine of Artillery, his chiefe Ammunition, his head quarters are there, eſpecially if any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent Prieſts ſteeped in the gall of Antichriſtianiſme be among them: It is moſt requiſite that ſuch meetings, ſuch places be diſſolved. I could wiſh that garriſon of rancorous and imbittered ſpirit were utterly ſlighted and demoliſhed in us all; this one thing hath overthrowne whole Kingdomes many times <note n="c" place="margin">vid. Jun orat. Tom. 1 orat. 1 de colleg. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia &amp; orat. 2.</note>; God forbid it ſhould act its part among us, I truſt God will never give us over to that unquiet, deſtructive ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God hath in a ſtrange manner purged out from among you many rotten members, which you could never have caſt out, if they had not excommunicated themſelves, by a voluntary ſeparation and baniſhment from you, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate engagement againſt you; ſo that in this reſpect it may moſt truly be ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of gratitude, you muſt fall to purging and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; God hath ſhewed you the way, who hath diſtinguiſhed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113723:18"/> betwixt the precious and the vile, which you muſt alſo doe; for the iron and clay will never incorporate, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 42. take heed you doe not give the Lord occaſion to ſay, as it is <hi>Ezek. 24. 6,-13. Her ſcumme is not yet gone out. In thy filthineſſe is lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; becauſe I have purged thee and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſſe any more, till I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee.</hi> The ſcum of ſwearers, drunkards, &amp;c. abounds among us. But beſides theſe, there is a more dangerous ſort of people of choyce parts, poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of Antichriſt, of as croſſe a grain to reformation as any men whatſoever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoaked in malignity; if theſe have the liberty of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, they have liberty and opportunity to diffuſe their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; theſe ought to be purged out of Pulpits eſpecially. It is reported of <hi>Cato Cenſor,</hi> when <hi>Carneades</hi> the Philoſopher came to <hi>Rome</hi> in an Embaſſie, that the young men of <hi>Rome</hi> flockt to him, being allured with the ſweetneſſe and majeſty of his eloquence and learning, gave counſell in open Senate, that they ſhould give him diſpatch with all ſpeed, leaſt he ſhould infect and inchant the minds and affections of the Youth, and bring in an alteration of the manners and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the ſtate. <hi>Cato's</hi> advice will ſuit well with this which is propounded concerning ſuch men before ſpoken of: You have an Univerſity and a Kingdome to purge, which lyes like the Augean Stable, and it is a very vaſt buſineſſe to doe it; but as it is reported of <hi>Hercules,</hi> being to cleanſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean Stable (in which was kept three thouſand Kine, and it had not been cleanſed for thirty yeers together) but <hi>Hercules</hi> letting in the River <hi>Alpheus,</hi> did that with eaſe which was thought impoſſible: So you by letting in the waters of the Sanctuary ſpoke of, <hi>Ezek. 47. 2. The River which refreſheth the houſe of God ſhall purge it;</hi> ſo ſhall it be ſaid, What have you wrought?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Lord hath protected you in a moſt ſtrange and admirable manner, ſo that it may be ſaid, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> by way of gratitude be you a ſword and a ſhield; to the truth a ſhield, and to errour and hereſie a ſword: It was ſaid of <hi>Fabius,</hi> that he was <hi>Romanorum clypeus,</hi> and of <hi>Marcellus</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113723:19"/> that he was <hi>Romanorum enſis,</hi> becauſe it was the chiefe care of the firſt, to ſafeguard his Souldiers from the danger of <hi>Annibal,</hi> and of the other to deſtroy him: Certainly it may be ſaid of you as it was Deut. 33. 29. <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael; who is like unto thee O people! ſaved by the Lord the ſhield of thy help, and who is theſword of thy excellency: and thine enemies ſhall be found lyars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, the Lord hath appeared eminently in executing judgement on your enemies; we may ſay, as it is <hi>Pſal. 9. 16. The Lord is knowne by the judgement which he executeth, the wicked is ſnared in the work of his owne hand:</hi> Higgajon Selah. by way of gratitude doe juſtice, execute right judgement. There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſad complaints of partiality and affection in Committees, of retarding of cauſes, of pleading for delinquents, of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of right, it is <hi>vox populi,</hi> which is ſometime called <hi>vox Dei:</hi> It was your honour to put downe thoſe bloody Courts of the Star-chamber and High-commiſſion, and the arbitrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the Councell-table, and I hope it ſhall be your care that there be not a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a tranſlation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thoſe Courts into the Parliament; they did turne judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into wormwood, and leave off righteouſneſſe, as it is <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 7. but I hope that judgement ſhall now run downe as waters, and judgement as a mighty ſtreame, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to have any thing to doe with his people, till they came to doe juſtice, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 16, 17. then ſayes he, <hi>Come let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> the Lord preſſeth it on them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the Lord hath done great things for us in the ſurrender of OXFORD; if all things be well conſidered it is a great mercy: The ſtrength of the place, the proviſions of all kinds within; the reſolution of the men to hold out a ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſiege, the danger of demoliſhing an Univerſity, famous as any in the world, the danger of breaking our Army; the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which hereby we have of being aſſiſtant to <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with the advantages that you may have of promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the reformation, in that place above others; all theſe put together make it a great mercy.</p>
            <p>Now by way of gratitude, make it your buſineſſe and care
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113723:19"/> now to purge and reforme that place above others: Give me leave to propound ſome things to your conſideration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that place, with ſubmiſſion ſtill to your wiſdome herein: I doe it the rather becauſe I know there ought to be had a more then ordinary care of ſuch places as that is; for a Fountaine, a Garden and a Nurſery muſt in a ſpeciall manner be lookt unto; for it is a rule that <hi>quod initio eſt vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, tractu temporis non convaleſcet;</hi> and it is a rule concerning Phyſick, that an errour in the firſt concoction is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in the ſecond; beſides, there ought to be a ſpeciall care of what is put into new and freſh Veſſels, and what mold is to be laid on tender plants and young trees: theſe things laid together, make me the bolder to propound ſome things to your wiſdome, with reference to that place.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if there be any ſuch to be found there, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of neceſſity have been conſtrained to live in that place; yet they have that mark on their fore-heads, which is to cry <note n="a" place="margin">What <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſpeaks of a Prince I doubt not but you will obſerve, <hi>Non poena ſemper ſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius poenitentia contentus eſſe.</hi> Agric. <hi>Poenam igitur si tuto poterus, dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis; sin minus, temperabis,</hi> Sen. dc Clem. 1.</note> for alll the abominations of it, as it is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. 4. or if there be any that ſhall be found, which now remember their doings and wayes, wherein they have defiled themſelves, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 43. if there be any ſuch who (whatſoever they have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore) epiſcopall, &amp;c. yet if now they ſhall doe that hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which the adverſaries of the captivity did but pretend to doe <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 1, 2. help you to build, and ſeek God as you doe, if perhaps in all things they ſhall not come up to cloſe with every particular with you, yet they will be quiet, will not oppoſe or hinder you: I hope you will doe by theſe as <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> did by them that were not cleanſed, and did eat the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over otherwiſe then was written, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 18. he prayed for them, the Lord pardon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that prepare their heart to ſeek the Lord, &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. and <hi>ver.</hi> 22. he ſpake comfortably to the Levites, &amp;c. Not that I would have a toleration of practice for any error, but a tender uſage and reſpect to ſuch, of whom we cannot ſay, they will not, but for want rather of a cleerer diſcovery, have not, doe not ſee what for the future perhaps they may aſſent unto: It ſhall be your glory to recover and gaine ſuch as theſe with love and the ſpirit of meekneſs, rather then to caſt them out <note n="b" place="margin">—<hi>Peragit tranquilla po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testas quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olenta nequit, mandataque fortius urget Imperioſa qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi>—Claud. Paneg. <hi>Adhibenda eſt moderatio, quae ſanabilia inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma distingucre a deploratis ſcia,</hi> Sen de Clem. 1.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113723:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, if upon due ſearch made and cognizance had, you find that the Fountaine is become bitter, like the water of Marah, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 23. if there be <hi>mors in olla,</hi> as there was in that pot which was ſet on for the ſonnes of the Prophets, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. 38, 40. if it be found that the ſalt of the earth be unſavoury, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 13. if the light be extinguiſhed; if it be ſo that the Garden be overgrowne with Nettles and Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Weeds <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Infoelix lolium, &amp; ſteriles dominantur avenae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pro molli viola, ac purpureo narciſſo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carduus, &amp; ſpinis ſurgit palinurus acutis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Virgil.</l>
                  </lg>
               </note>, and Thornes.</p>
            <p>If <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <p>Whither that of <hi>Fr. Petrach</hi> concerning <hi>Rome,</hi> may not in ſome ſort be true here let others judge.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Errorum ludus, ſectarum nobile templum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roma quidem fueras, nunc es Babylonia fallax,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ex qua tot luctus, gemituſque feruntur in orbem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O fraudum mater, carcer teterrimus irae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carnificina boni, ſed iniqui ſedula nutrix.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </note> it be found that ſhe which ſhould have been a mother, hath proved a ſtep-dame; if that which ſhould have been a nurſery of holineſſe and Religion, be found a ſinke of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe; if that place which ſhould have been a mint of the precious coyne, that ſhould paſſe currant every where without controll or contradiction, be found to be a forge of counterfeit coyne and falſhoods, againſt God and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; if that which ſhould have been a <hi>Goſhen</hi> be found an <hi>Aegypt</hi> rather; if that which ſhould have been as <hi>Zion</hi> be a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and that which ſhould have been as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be a <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> then I know every one will ſay, you had need beſtir your ſelves here above all other places whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But what is here to be done? I dare appeale to prudentiall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113723:20"/> men among our adverſaries: Put the caſe the Parliament had poſſeſſed <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the Divines which adhered to that had ſheltred themſelves there, and were in all thoſe places of maintainance and truſt which they have which are oppoſite to the Parliament and their cauſe: had the King prevailed and taken the place, as now you have done, I appeale to any impartiall men, what would they have done? you may if you pleaſe make that good, the children of this world are wiſer in their generation then the children of light; I doe beleeve it ſhould never have come into debate, whither you or any that have eminently engaged for and with you, ſhould have compounded for eſtates; it may be you would have thought it happineſſe and favour enough to have redeemed your lives. Theſe things being premiſed, and there be truth in theſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, then I think you need not have any one to tell you what to doe; never any did begin a plantation among weeds and brambles.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, theſe be men of excellent parts and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate learning; what ſhall we doe with them? I anſwer, as one ſayes of the Jeſuits, <hi>quo meliores eò deteriores,</hi> concerning whom I ſay further, as <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> did of his adverſary <hi>Farnaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, talis cum ſis, utinam noſter eſſes:</hi> I could wiſh for my owne part that all wayes were uſed to gaine them, if it might be; and I could wiſh heartily that the Univerſity had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered as well as the Garriſon, and Chriſt had captivated learning, as our Army did the Militia, and that the <hi>Militia togata</hi> as well as <hi>armata,</hi> (I could wiſh they had been diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) had yeelded up it ſelfe to God and you: Put the caſe they have been never ſo bad, and have appeared never ſo much againſt you, yet if they ſhall doe as <hi>Benbadads</hi> ſervants did to the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Behold we have heard that the Kings of Iſrael are mercifull Kings,</hi> and they put <note n="e" place="margin">—Ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere pulchrut iam miſero, pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeque genus vidiſſe precan tem, <hi>Claud.</hi>
               </note> ſack-cloath on their loynes and ropes on their heads, and ſo they came to him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20. 30, 31, 32. if thoſe that have publiſhed you Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in the Preſſe, and preached you Rebels in the Pulpit, and diſcourſed you Rebels in their conference, and fought againſt you as Rebels, in the Field, yet if they ſhall doe as <hi>Benba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dads</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113723:21"/> ſervants did, I ſuppoſe you would let them know, you are ſuch abſolute conquerours of your ſelves, that you can and will pardon ſuch; and likewiſe beſtow (where no reward is due, but the moſt extreame puniſhment) favours and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence. I doe beleeve that many of them will never put you to it, to turne them out, if you would hire them to keep their preferments with great rewards, upon your termes, they would not doe it; nay, rather then uſe the Directory, take the Covenant, ſubmit to the Diſcipline, ſtoop to Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary power, promote your deſignes, engage in your way of reformation, all which are contrary to their principles (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe your conqueſts have had the like effect which <hi>Peters</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon had, or that God hath wrought upon them) they will ſuffer very much, rather then goe againſt their conſciences, in ſubmitting to that which they cannot ſubſcribe to.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I hope you will have an extraordinary care in the placing of fit men in the Univerſity: There be three ſorts of men you are to look after: Firſt, profeſſors of languages and ſciences: Secondly, Governours of houſes: Thirdly, Fellowes and Schollers. As for the firſt, if <hi>England</hi> cannot furniſh you, I hope <hi>Europe</hi> will; for if there be one better then another, let him be the man, whatever it coſt: theſe are fathers in the faculty, and progagate the ſciences; they have the wardſhip of learning committed to them: theſe Fathers of the Arts if they have not drawne in the maſculine vigour and life of the Muſes, they beget but a weak and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed iſſue: It is here as with naturall Parents, ſtrong and able Parents have like Progeny <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quanta per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicacia in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem, tanta be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficentia ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces utendum</hi> Tac. Ann. 12.</note>; beſides, he that undertakes <note place="margin">g <hi>Fortes crean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fortibus, &amp; bonis; eſt in juvencis; eſt in equis patrum virtus, nec im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellom feroces Progenerant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baus,</hi> Hor. l. 4. od. 4.</note> ſuch places upon a ſmall and weak foundation, it is as if he ſhould traverſe the Ocean in a Cock-boat, ſuch run a hazard from the Haven, and are like to prove famous onely by their errours and delinquencies.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort that we are to ſpeak of, is Governours of houſes, of whom there ought to be had by ſo much the greater care, by how much the greater influence they are like to have, and impreſſion on others, what the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſuch as are to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Scripture,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113723:21"/> ſhould be found in ſuch as are to be heads of Houſes; men exemplary in holineſſe and grace, whoſe life (as one ſpeaks of the life of a Prince) ſhould be <note n="h" place="margin">Pan. Troj.</note> 
               <hi>cenſura publica,</hi> as a publick ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dard, leſt haply if they come to be engaged in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or ſinfull courſe, <note n="i" place="margin">Sen. cont. 1.</note> 
               <hi>imitatio alienae oulpae</hi> be counted <hi>innocentia:</hi> the deformities &amp; infirmities of ſuch as we love &amp; honour, ſo often are doted on, and made patternes of our imitation: Men <note n="k" place="margin">—Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micae tur pia deciplunt cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum vitia, aut etiam ipſa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectant vetuti Balbinum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pus agnae. Hor. Serm. l. 1. Sat. 3.</note> of ſingular ſelf-deniall, and of a ſtrict converſation, are the fitteſt for ſuch places: that which <hi>Cicero</hi> notes as an errour in <hi>Cato</hi> the ſecond, when he writes to his friend <hi>Atticus,</hi> I take as a vertue required in a Governour; <hi>Cato optime ſentit</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſed nocet interdum Reip. loquitur enim tanquam in Rep. Platonis, non tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in faece Romuli.</hi> There is in ſome an eminent ſuitableneſſe of ſpirit, a notable frame of heart fitting a man for government; this is of great concernment; and although perhaps there may be wanting ſome perfections and accompliſhments which others have, yet there may be enough in theſe, thus qualified as I have ſpoken, to doe the work. It was ſaid by <hi>Themistocles</hi> being asked to touch a Lute, that he could not fiddle, but he could make a ſmall Towne, a great State: what he ſpake ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly of himſelfe, may be truly ſaid of theſe, that though they cannot fiddle, yet (through the bleſſing of God) they, of a place infamous for the preſent, may make a glorious Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity. There is an Academicall genius which animates ſome men, and ſuch will live beſt in that element which is moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall: Perhaps ſome may be thought on that are of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent parts, and fit for honourable employments, who may be thought to put downe others; yet as it was noted of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> that he would needs undertake to correct a curious Muſician in his art; but he was anſwered by him, God forbid that your fortune ſhould be ſo bad, as to know theſe things better then I: This may be ſaid in this caſe; ſome men have ſerved ſeverall apprentiſhips in the Univerſity, and of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity have been engaged in the ſtudies of the Arts, and ſuch kind of learning; and have been engaged in a way of employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which may be counted below the education of ſuch whoſe fortunes have afforded a ſubſiſtence otherwayes, and ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113723:22"/> by this means are brought into a capacity and fitneſſe for that place which is not proper for another. Let them be men of gravity and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <note n="l" place="margin">In that queſtion an <hi>Juvenes in numerum conciliario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum principis cooptandi ſint?</hi> the ſame that is ſaid againſt them will hold good here. Vid. Tiraq de jure primig. praef. n. 9 1. Bodin de Rep. l. 3. c. 1. <hi>Non poſſunt (inquit) u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venes in concione Pop. quae utiba ſunt ac iusta, perſuadere: nec ſenibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ec iuvenibus probantur, al eri enim idae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſe illis aequales, alteri ſapientia ſuperiores arbitrantur.</hi> Pet. Gregor. l. 24. de Rep. c. <hi>expedit omnino iuxta an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſas arbores plantas novas in ſerere, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> whoſe experience and yeers, together with their wiſe and ſober carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age puts a majeſty on go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſtrikes an awe and reſpect in others to reverence and honour the place for the Perſons ſake. Let them be ſuch who ſhall be able and meet, and will reſolve to beare the burden and heat of the day, and who ſhall in their owne perſons, not by proxies or deputation, diſcharge the duty of the place they ſhall be called unto.</p>
            <p>The third ſort, which are Scholers and fellows of houſes, to be choſen to places, I may ſpare my paines concerning them; yet I hope you will take ſpeciall care that ſuch places as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore were, may not be vendible things; but that parts and and learning may be the onely friends to plead for ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. What was ſaid of <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vendit</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, altaria, Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ille prius, vendere iure poteſt. Vid.</hi> Ideam reformand. Antichriſt. <hi>Vid.</hi> Busbaq. Ep. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, may be too truly ſaid of ſome in places of government: Welfare the Turks, whoſe cuſtome it is to preferre none but ſuch whoſe parts and endowments have advanced them above others. I might here take occaſion to repreſent the many defects and indeed diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that are in Grammer-Schooles: Firſt, in regard all are taken into Schooles without any reſpect to the capacity, or to future employments, whence many inconveniences doe ariſe: Secondly, many that are ſet to be Maſters and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of others, doe not onely want skill in the Languages, but alſo that genius and dexterity whereby they ſhould have a ſutableneſſe to the forming of that <hi>ulum &amp; molle lutum</hi> which is in children; there is great cunning in fitting the ſeed to the ſoyle: Thirdly, the anticipation and preoccupating of time; many will venture to goe before they can ſtand, and to the Univerſity they muſt goe, whereas it were fitter for them to be under the <hi>ferula.</hi> What an abſurd thing is it to come to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113723:22"/> the Univerſity to conſtrue Logick with the help of a Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary: we feele the miſerable effect of theſe things, and I might ſet downe much more, but that I hope you will have all the grievances in this kind preſented to you from the hands of them that have better skill.</p>
            <p>Your third care muſt be concerning the preſent and future peace of the Church, which depends much upon the correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence of judgement and opinion among them which ſhall be placed in the Univerſity; for if that prove a Seminary of diviſion, and a ſeed plot of ſchiſme and contention, it will not end where it began, but as water from a Fountaine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth, and ſparkles from a common fire ſcatter, ſo will it be here: Of what ſad conſequence had it like to have proved, the diviſion betwixt Doctor <hi>Whitaker regius</hi> profeſſor in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and <hi>Petrus Baro Margaret</hi> profeſſor; they going con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary one to the other in ſome great poynts of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: <note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>De amiſſione gratiae.</hi> 2 <hi>De certitudine ſalutis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baro</hi> affirming, and <hi>Whitaker</hi> denying? by meanes of which, one ſayes there was great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction among the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the Univerſity <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Profeſſorum diſputatio (ut ſolet) inventutem diu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> partes traxit, &amp;c.</hi> Manuſcript lat. hac de re.</note>: what miſerable confuſion and diſtraction did the contention breed in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, which aroſe from <hi>Arminius</hi> profeſſor at <hi>Leyden,</hi> who was oppoſed by <hi>Franciſcut Gomarus,</hi> in that grand controverſie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the abſolute Decree <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Arminius tenuit, Deum non abſolute quoſdam homines, ex ſolo beneplacito ſuo, ſed poſt lapſum, iterum per fidem in Christum credentes ad aeternam beatitudinem ordinaſſe; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer de Reprobatione, nem nem abſolute, ſed ob infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Reprob sic deo prateritos &amp; aternis poenis deſtin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos:</hi> Gomarus <hi>pro ſententia contraria disputationem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit:</hi> Vid. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſſect. Belgii per Solom. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotum.</note>? Of what ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence was that difference between <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> and <hi>Johan. Chryſastomus,</hi> concerning the Books of <hi>Origen;</hi> the former condemning of them, and the latter appoving them? thoſe that loved neither of them, made uſe of theſe coales between them, to ſet on fire the Church of God: Theſe two famous and renowned Fathers fell into bitter language one againſt another, and meeting one another, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaid
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113723:23"/> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome, ſpero be minime moriturum epiſcopum, Johannes:</hi> And <hi>Johannes Chryſoſt.</hi> to him againe, <hi>ſpero te minime ad eccleſiam tuam rediturum:</hi> Both theſe paſſionate ſpeeches proved true in the event <note n="q" place="margin">Eccleſ. vetus. Nov. edit. cura Abrah. Sculteti. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. 4.</note>. How all ſorts of people ſuffer many times in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of learned men, we are able to ſpeak, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſtory fully repreſents <note n="r" place="margin">Videl. l. 3. c. 2. de prudentia vet. eccleſ.</note>. I could alſo relate divers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> to this purpoſe, when thoſe fancies and opinions of the Arminians, Socinians, Pelagians, Semipelagians, Papiſts, &amp;c. began to gather ſtrength among us: it may be in leſſer differences (as <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ut in fidibus ac tibiis atque cantu ipſo ac vocibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centus eſt quidam tenendus, &amp;c.</hi> l. 2. de civit. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Austin</hi> ſpeaks of diſſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy in the ſtrings of an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there may be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: and as <hi>Junius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, there may be ſome good come from <note n="t" place="margin">Jun. orat. 7. de colleg. concord. <hi>ut hoſtis muris ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per imminens facit ut circumſpecta &amp; ſolicita civitas sit, sic ſententiarum diversitate fit, ut nihil agatur dicaturque temere, &amp;c.</hi> Camerar. l. 3. c. 6. Hor. Subſeciv.</note> them; yet in theſe greater points of controverſie, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there be the ſaddeſt effects: and therefore I hope it ſhall be your care to place ſuch there who ſhall be of one mind, and walke by the ſame rule as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            <p>4ly. let it be your ſpeciall care that all due encouragements to learning be continued, and what are wanting may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: It hath been a reproach (and it is well it is a reproach) caſt on the Parliament, that you are no friends to the Muſes: What <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid 1 <hi>Sam. 22. 7. Will the Son of Jeſſe give every one of you Fields and Vineyard, &amp;c.</hi> hath in like manner been ſaid of you: will the Parliament make you Biſhops and Deanes, &amp;c. It is confeſſed they will not; but they ſhall doe better if they take their revenues, and diſpoſe of them ſo as to ſupply the defects and wants of many, which heretofore did maintaine the luſt and pride of one or few: The Lord himſelfe hath had a great care of preſerving Learning and the Arts, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he hath couched all kind of learning in the bowels of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113723:23"/> Scripture: He hath alſo ſtill in his providence, raiſed up ſome or other to maintaine and ſupport it, when it hath been moſt violently aſſaulted. Beſides, we find that there is a neere affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity betwixt learning and Religion; hence it is that ſtill the Libraries and Churches joyned neer together; the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens did obſerve ſo much: As in <hi>Rome,</hi> the Library in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll, and <hi>Augustus</hi> Library neer the Temple of <hi>Apollo:</hi> So <hi>Trajan</hi> and <hi>Domitian</hi> did the like, and ſo have Chriſtian Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; the reaſon is given, <hi>quad Religionem fine libris non conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari putarunt</hi> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>De legibus</hi> Conſtant. Baldwin. Socrat. l. 7. c. 25. Euſeb. in vita <hi>Conſtantin.</hi> l. 1. c. 35.</note>: <hi>Constantine, Theodoſins,</hi> &amp;c. have been eminent examples in this kind, for advancing and favouring both learning and Religion.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I hope you will endeavour to ſettle a faithfull, able godly Miniſtry in that place, and there is as much cauſe as in any place (I doe beleeve) in <hi>England;</hi> for that place which hath or ſhould have bin a <hi>Goſhen</hi> for light, hath had Aegyptian dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in it, ignorance of Chriſt in the midſt of the Schooles of the Prophets; the very ſalt-pit hath proved unſavoury in a great meaſure; the eye hath been bloodſhot or dark, or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ill humours; the breaſts have had little or no milk; there htth been a Wilderneſſe in that Garden, and drought in the midſt of plenty; there is ſcarcely more rudeneſſe, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance &amp; barbariſme in the Kingdome then in that very place: I need not ſpend much time in this, for you have begun that work already, and I doe not doubt but it will be your care to promote and continue it; ſo by this meanes I hope it ſhall be ſaid as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. 1, 2, &amp;c. <hi>Sing O barren thou that didſt not bear; break forth into ſinging, and cry aloud thou that didſt not travell with child, for more are the children of the deſolate then the children of the married wife; enlarge the place of thy Tent, &amp;c.</hi> By your care (I hope) the Wilderneſſe and the ſolitary places ſhall be glad, and the deſert ſhall rejoyce and bloſſome as the Roſe; it ſhall bloſſome abundantly and rejoyce even with joy and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and the glory of <hi>Lebanon</hi> ſhall be given unto It, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of <hi>Carmel</hi> and <hi>Sharon.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 1, 2. I hope as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7, &amp;c. that it ſhall be fulfilled, <hi>The eyes of the blind ſhall be opened, and the eares of the deaf ſhall be unſtopped, and</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113723:24"/> 
               <hi>the lame man ſhall leap as an Hart, and the tongue of the dumb ſhall ſing, for in the Wilderneſſe ſhall waters break out, and ſtreames in the deſert, &amp;c.</hi> I hope the Lord will ſay to that place as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. 11, 12, &amp;c. <hi>Behold, I will lay thy foundations with Saphires, and I will make thy windowes of Agates, and thy gates of Carbuncles, and all thy borders pleaſant ſtones, and all thy children ſhall be taught of God, &amp;c.</hi> I hope that the propheſie, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. ſhall have its accompliſhment in a great meaſure there, and that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall flow from thence, ſhall riſe up to the neck, and that every thing which liveth and moveth in thoſe waters ſhall live, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. and that all trees ſhall be planted by thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which ſhall bring forth their fruit in ſeaſon, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. If it be your care (as I hope it will) thus to lay out your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and paines in this place, as I have preſented to you, it ſhall be your crowne and comfort, and poſterity I hope ſhall have cauſe to ſay, as it is <hi>Iſa. 25. 1. O Lord thou art my God, I will exalt thee, I will prayſe thy name, for thou haſt done won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113723:24"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Die Mercurii 22. Julii</hi> 1646.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that Maſter <hi>Henry Herbert</hi> doe from this Houſe give thankes unto Maſter <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> for the great paines he tooke in the Sermon he preached yeſterday at the entreaty of this Houſe at St. <hi>Margarets Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> (it being the day of publique thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving) and to deſire him to print his Sermon; and he is to have the like priviledge in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it as others in the like kind uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
